when you're a professional voiceover
you're paid to record clients scripts so
that on playback it sounds like the
words are spoken naturally and not as if
you're merely reading words off a script
that someone has given you money to read
there are sometimes subtle and sometimes
not so subtle but important nuances of a
human voice that subconsciously tell the
listener whether you are and living
speaking out loud your thoughts or just
reading a pre-prepared script now
obviously professional film and stage
actors need to sound natural and
believable or US audiences would be
walking out of cinemas and theaters when
they said can we voice actors learn
similar skills of course well first let
me give you a quick acting example in
two takes spot the difference men it
doesn't look good look we've simply run
out of time men it doesn't look good
look with we've simply run out of time
all right so what are the differences
well in the more realistic second take
there are plenty of imperfections the
pauses the differences in voice levels
the pace of speech the heavy breathing
the sighing the second take is the
performance that sounds outlived and not
just read from a script it would be even
better of course if I was a decent actor
but it proves a point but of course for
the types of scripts we normally had
voiceovers don't have the same
parameters as stage actors for our
narrations we call and put imperfections
in our speed of speech and voice volume
usually needs to be the same throughout
the script and breaths are not really
welcome are they so what can we do well
it depends what kind of voiceover script
you get given and the style required you
may get a script that is actually needed
in a style that sounds like it is read
like in a 1980s cheesy game show or
something the very best prizes are on
offer tonight with the stars
prai's an amazing new speedboat
but most of the time well we'll probably
get given corporate narrations maybe
talking about a new engineering process
or a promo video script about a new
service or a product so here's how to
deliver your voice recordings that your
client will absolutely love and invite
you back again firstly you need to sound
like you are the proud owner of the
company that's featured in your
corporate script or that you're the
inventor or the divisor of the product
or service featured in the promotion
script or whatever and you've put up
your home for the loan to develop it in
other words you need to totally and
utterly own the script and be passionate
about the content this is not to say you
have to give an over-the-top
enthusiastic the man agreed for every
script you need to read in a style and
speed that's suitable to the script all
that you've been asked to deliver by the
client but your voice should sound
confident you should sound proud of what
you're talking about in any style of
voice whether soft and intimate or a
shouty hard sell or anything in between
and and by having this sort of proud
confident mindset your voice in delivery
should automatically sound much more
natural and not give away that you're
reading a script now this skill to sell
natural will come with experience but
when you're starting out follow this
guide read and understand the script
just totally get your head around it
ask any questions to the client that you
need so you know the backstory to the
script you need to know who the finished
media is going to be aimed at is it
targeted at an audience internal to the
organization to be played as a rousing
conference Oprah or is it a soft sell
aimed at the end user one that's just
meant to raise the profile of the
company then go through the script
underline the words that need to be
emphasized sometimes clients will
already make it clear the words in the
script that need to be emphasized
usually it's obvious but even if you
disagree with what they're asking for
you must remember the client is always
right but it's usually the ad
in the script they need a bit of punch
here an example coming up soon by the
way secondly be physical be physical
when recording this will help you it
helps us all you won't believe how
important this is and till you do it and
then you'll hear the difference nobody
can see you in the voice booth
don't be embarrassed so move around and
feel the fashion that you should feel
physically act the script just give it
your all as you punch the air for the
emphasis words and toss your head with a
flourish for the final payoff of the
script act it you'll see me doing this
and make a fool of myself but no one
watches me in a minute now you won't
need to do this as much if it's an
informational script or elearning or a
phone prompt but honestly don't be
afraid of moving around and using your
hands and arms to help flow and
structure
now this physicality I suggest when
you're recording voiceovers is very
important and makes the difference
between an okay voice over recording and
a brilliant one using my hands now I'm
doing yeah I'm probably putting you know
it's a kind of distracting to you
watching me use my hands but you see if
I was doing a voice over you wouldn't
see the flippin hands but it helps me to
project in fact if you have a difficult
turn of phrase or a long sentence where
you really can't take a breath what
you've got to do it you know moving and
rolling your arms gently as if you're
describing what you're saying will often
help you and underline the certain words
it's really weird but it works if you
don't believe me try it
thirdly to keep the recording natural in
edit avoid doing edits that would make
it sound artificial in other words
usually you would not cut out breaths
you would leave the duration of the
breaths in to your edit but you would
highlight them and reduce the volume you
go phase then paid it by 10 to 12
decibels something like that so it's
still there so it doesn't sound like
it's cutting out and it's over and above
highlighting the breast making them
completely silent which sounds terrible
sounds weird or just deleting them so
you end up with sentences butted up like
a commercial radio news bulletin a very
unnatural sound so to sum up one
own the script really believe in it and
if it's that type of script be an
ambassador for the organization or the
company
all right promoting the product or
service be confident emphasize the right
words in a natural way be passionate
about it
secondly don't be a rigid behind the
microphone people aren't like this in
real life when they're in conversation
notice people when they talk they're
moving around doing stuff you know use
your arms and hands to help the delivery
but obviously don't hit the microphone
or move your mouth too far away from the
mic capsule and thirdly make sure when
you're editing your recording together
you keep the transitions natural they're
my three main pointers now here's an
example it's an actual short script I
had as a job
I'll read it first not following any of
the advice I've just given I won't own
it in any way I'll be stiff and rigid
behind the microphone and I'll hackle
the breath out in edit later for you
okay
here we go Tierra presents the most
sustainable blend of the Tierra range
Tierra India a unique premium blend of
refined Indian coffee coffee was
introduced in India over 400 years ago
in the legendary Babu Dan brought the
precious beans from Yemen today India is
the only country which grows all coffee
crops in shade Sierra India contains
coffee from the sustainability project
in Karnataka state where Lavazza
Foundation supports over 1,000
smallholder coffee farming families
improving coffee quality and
competitiveness through sustainable
agricultural practices and motivating
women's participation in the value chain
to preserve the coffee aroma Sierra
India blend is roasted directly in India
with the slow delicate and gentle
roasting process the in cup result is a
sumptuous creamy espresso a rich and
velvety body with notes of cocoa and
spices hints of licorice
Teairra India a unique story of taste
and sustainability and now I'm gonna
follow my advice and I hope you'll
notice the difference Tierra presents
the most sustainable blend of the Tierra
range Tierra India
a unique premium blend of refined Indian
coffee coffee was introduced in India
over 400 years ago when the legendary
Babu Dan brought the precious beans from
he-man and today India is the only
country which grows all coffee crops in
shade
Teairra India contains coffee from the
sustainability project in Karnataka
state where Lavazza Foundation supports
over 1,000 smallholder coffee farming
families improving coffee quality and
competitiveness through sustainable
agricultural practices and motivating
women's participation in the value chain
to preserve the coffee aromas Teairra
India blend is roasted directly in India
with the slow delicate and gentle
roasting process the in cup result is a
sumptuous creamy espresso a rich and
velvety body with notes of cocoa and
spices hints of licorice tea era India a
unique story of taste and sustainability
well there you go
if you're a quite new to voiceover work
you need to read and record a lot of
varied scripts every day play your
recordings back over good quality
loudspeakers criticized your performance
ask a good friend or family member to
give their feedback as well if
appropriate and over time you'll be able
to self-direct and monitor yourself life
I have you've been on one of my other
courses I call this the third head
technique after the old tape recorders
they had three heads the first one a
raised second one recorded third one
played you see the third tape head
played back a split second after the
second tape head recorded something and
you develop a similar mental technique
you'll do this in your brain by speaking
and monitoring what you are saying at
the same time it's really clever how
your brain can do this so you'll stop
when you've made a mistake or stop when
you know you could have just said
something better it's almost uncanny how
the human brain can do this but myself
and thousands of other experienced voice
actors do this regularly every day so
you need to get this in your repertoire
well good luck in your ongoing
development keep it natural and if you'd
like to know more about any of our voice
training modules and courses go -
voiceover masterclass comm thanks for
watching